[
  {
    "question": "Q. What is general revelation (also known as natural revelation) with biblical references?",
    "answer": "A. General revelation, or book of nature (Psalm 19), is the revelation of God through creation, God's self-disclosure through his works. We receive it by reason and perception. It shows that there is a God and that humans are accountable to him, but cannot save mankind.<br><br>Psalm 19:1-6; Acts 17; Romans 1-2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is special revelation?",
    "answer": "A. Special Revelation is God's self-disclosure through speech and written testimony received by faith, revealing to us all our spiritual benefits (Rom. 8) and how we must be saved (Eph. 2:8-9).<br><br>Psalm 19:7-12; 2 Peter 1:20-21; 2 Timothy 3:15-16; Hebrews 1:1-2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is plenary, verbal inspiration?",
    " answer": "A. Plenary, verbal inspiration refers to the belief that the inspiration of Scripture extends to every word written in them, such that not a single word in the original autographa was written outside the influence of the Holy Spirit."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the necessity of Scripture?",
    "answer": "A. Scripture is necessary because no one can divine the mind of God. His purpose and will have to be revealed by special revelation for us to know it. Scripture is necessary for saving faith, often called 'the seed of the church', and remains necessary until time ends (Rom. 10:17)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the authority of Scripture?",
    "answer": "A. Scripture is inherently authoritative by virtue of its Holy Spirit inspiration. It holds historical authority in that it is 100% historically reliable. It holds normative authority in that it is God’s rule of life and conduct. (2 Tim 3:16-17)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the sufficiency of Scripture?",
    "answer": "A. The “sufficiency” of scripture posits that the cannon is closed. We have nothing to add and there will be nothing to add – the scriptures are sufficient as they reveal the mysteries of the covenant of Grace which is completely fulfilled in Jesus Christ, the Alpha and Omega of our faith and existence. Scripture is complete, containing all that is needed for God's glory and for man's salvation, faith, and life. (WCF 1.6) The sufficiency of Scripture ensures that all aspects of pastoral ministry are rooted in God’s complete and authoritative Word."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is meant by the perspicuity of Scripture?",
    "answer": "A. Scripture was given in a common, simple language that can be understood in its plain sense by those of sound mind; the knowledge of saving faith is clearly and simply presented in Scripture, allowing anyone who earnestly seeks salvation to easily gain this knowledge for themselves, without relying on the church or a priesthood (WCF 1.7; Psalm 19:7-8)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the difference between 'inspiration' and 'illumination'?",
    "answer": "A. Inspiration is the act of the Holy Spirit whereby He sovereignly guided and directed the authors of Scripture as they wrote. Illumination refers to the work of the Holy Spirit in believers which aids them in understanding the meaning of Scripture and its application to their lives."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Explain the redemptive-historical hermeneutical approach?",
    "answer": "A. The redemptive-historical hermeneutic interprets Scripture as a unified story of God's redemption, seeing each passage in light of its contribution to the overall narrative of salvation through Jesus Christ."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the most basic rule of interpreation flowing from the Reformation?",
    "answer": "A. Scripture interprets Scripture, the analogy of faith."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is meant by the Reformation doctrine of sola scriptura?",
    "answer": "A. Sola scriptura means that the Scriptures alone are the word of God, and there exists no unwritten word outside or alongside them with equal authority to bind the conscience. This implies the doctrine of <em>analogia fidei</em>, which states that the infallible rule for interpreting Scripture is Scripture itself."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Explain the doctrine of the Trinity?",
    "answer": "A. Short: There are three persons in the Godhead; the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost; and these three are one God, the same in substance, equal in power and glory.(WSC 6)<br>Long: In the unity of the Godhead there are three persons, of one substance, power, and eternity: God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghost. The Father is of none, neither begotten, nor proceeding; the Son is eternally begotten of the Father; the Holy Ghost eternally proceeding from the Father and the Son. (WCF 2.3)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are the personal properties of the Trinity?",
    "answer": "A. God the Father decrees (Dan 4:34-35; Eph 1:1-4). The Son is the eternally begotten son (filiation) of the Father, begotten not made (John 1:1,14; Heb 1:5; Ps. 2). The Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son (John 15:26-27)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are the Ontological and Economic Trinity?",
    "answer": "A. The Ontological Trinity refers to God as He is in Himself, describing the relationship between the persons in themselves without respect to creation or redemption. There is but one only, living, and true God (Deut. 6:4) who exists in three persons, of one substance, power, and eternity: God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit (Matt 3:16-17; Matt 28:19; 2 Cor 13:14). The Father is of none, neither begotten, not proceeding; the Son is eternally begotten of the Father (John 1:14, 18); the Holy Spirit eternally proceeding from the Father and the Son (John 15:26).<br><br>The Economic Trinity refers to God as He has revealed Himself to us, describing the relationship of the persons of the Trinity in the work of redemption and creation.<br>This distinction is important as it maintains that there is mystery in the Triune God beyond our capabilities to fully understand."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are the incommunicable attributes of God?",
    "answer": "A. Incommunicable attributes of God are:<br>1. Self-Existence/Aseity – God exists in himself (Gen 1:1; Dan 3:34-35; Jn 1:1-3; Ps 33:11; John 5:26)<br>2. Immutable – God does not change (Mal. 3:6; Num 23:19; Dan 3:35; Ps 33:11; Heb 6:17)<br>3. Infinity – (Ps 145:3; Acts 17:27)<br>4. Omniscient – (Psalm 115:3; 1 John 3:20)<br>5. Omnipotent – (Luke 1:37)<br>6. Omnipresent (Psalm 139; Jer. 23; Acts 17)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are the communicable attributes of God?",
    "answer": "A. Communicable attributes of God are:<br>1. Holiness – (Is. 6:3; Rev. 4:8)<br>2. Wisdom – (Rom. 11:33)<br>3. Love – (John 3:16; Eph. 2:8-9)<br>4. Grace – (Eph 2:7-9)<br>5. Justice – (Micah 6:8)<br>6. Truth (John 3:33; cf. Num. 23:19; Isa. 45:19; John 14:6)<br>7. Righteousness – (Psalm 1; Psalm 2:7)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Explain the doctrine of the incarnation.",
    "answer": "A. The eternal Son, the second person of the Trinity, took on flesh (in carne) and dwelt among us. Jesus Christ, while remaining fully God, became fully human. The doctrine of the incarnation is essential to the atoning work of Jesus by his living a perfect life while being truly human, thereby fulfilling the law's demands."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Sabellianism/Modalism?",
    "answer": "A. Teaches that the unipersonal God reveals himself in three ‘modes.’ Denies the real, eternal distinction of the divine persons. The three persons of the Trinity have no real and distinct existence apart from God’s interaction with the world. It is an attack on his <em>personal dignity</em>."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Subordinationism?",
    "answer": "A. Affirms a real distinction between the persons of a godhead, but the Son and Holy Spirit are subordinate to God the Father are not completely equal in power and glory. To be begotten causes the Son to be less than God, even if he is the most eminent of his creation and is an attack on his <em>true deity</em>."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Describe Christ's nature?",
    "answer": "A. Jesus Christ, being two whole, perfect, and distinct natures, the Godhead and the manhood, were inseparably joined together in one person, without conversion, composition, or confusion (WCF 8.2), being wholly human and wholly divine in a hypostatic union."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are Christ's offices?",
    "answer": "A. Christ executes the offices of Prophet, Priest, and King: revealing God's will for salvation, offering Himself as a sacrifice to reconcile us to God, and subduing and defending us as King."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the Penal Substitutionary Atonement theory?",
    "answer": "A. The view that the atonement was intended to propitiate God's wrath, reconciling sinners to Him, through a vicarious atonement where Christ atoned for sin, obtaining eternal redemption for man, by paying the price of penal justice we deserve."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Kenosis?",
    "answer": "A. Self-emptying, from Phil. 2:6-7. This has caused much controversy as to how and to what extent Christ emptied Himself. Some extremists say He emptied Himself of all divine attributes by becoming man – but our confession says He emptied Himself of only His glory by humbling Himself by becoming man.<br><br>Jesus was not divested of his divine attributes but entered into human flesh with his divine attributes intact. The act of the incarnation was a subtraction, but an addition. The passage fully affirms Jesus’ deity, being in the form of God, and the word appears within the section describing Jesus’ taking on a human form. The word expresses Jesus’ attitude toward his divine status—Jesus did not exploit his deity to keep him from fulfilling his task as our redeemer."
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe and defend substitutionary atonement.",
    "answer": "The substitutionary atonement of Christ is a doctrine rooted in both the Old and New Testaments. In the Old Testament, the sacrificial system, particularly the Passover (Ex. 12) and the Day of Atonement (Lev. 16), foreshadowed the ultimate sacrifice of Christ. The innocent lamb's blood was shed to cover the sins of the people, illustrating the principle of substitutionary atonement. In Is. 53, the Suffering Servant is described as bearing the iniquities of God's people, being pierced for their transgressions, and crushed for their iniquities.<br><br>The New Testament explicitly affirms this doctrine, with Jesus himself declaring, \"The Son of Man came not to be served but to serve, and to give his life as a ransom for many\" (Mark 10:45). The apostle Paul writes, \"For our sake he made him to be sin who knew no sin, so that in him we might become the righteousness of God\" (2 Cor. 5:21), and \"Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law by becoming a curse for us\" (Gal. 3:13). The substitutionary atonement of Christ is thus a doctrine that spans both Testaments, revealing God's plan to save humanity through the sacrifice of his beloved Son."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is universal atonement, and why is it refuted?",
    "answer": "A. Universal atonement is the idea that Christ's atoning sacrifice is for all people without exception, but it is refuted because it is inconsistent with Scripture's teaching on God's elect, and if some are condemned despite Christ's atonement, then it is lacking in efficacy."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is universalism, and why is it refuted?",
    "answer": "A. Universalism is the belief that all people will ultimately be saved and reconciled to God, but it is refuted because it fails to do justice to sin and its consequences, diminishes Jesus' final judgment, and undermines the importance of evangelism and mission."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Does the atonement of Christ save actually or potentially?",
    "answer": "A. Christ's atonement saves actually and completely, with no insufficiency in its nature or application."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are the Five Points of Calvinism?",
    "answer": "A. The Five Points of Calvinism, summarized by the acrostic TULIP, are: Total Depravity, Unconditional Election, Limited (Particular) Atonement, Irresistible Grace, and Perseverance of the Saints."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Total Depravity?",
    "answer": "A. Total Depravity is the doctrine that every aspect of man's life (mind, will, spirit, body, etc.) is affected by the fall and is in an estate of sin, yet man is not as bad as he can be due to God's common grace. (Rom. 1:18-3:23; Isaiah 53:6; Rom. 7-8)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Unconditional Election?",
    "answer": "A. Unconditional Election is the doctrine that God's election cannot be affected by any other power, including man, and that He has foreordained all things, and no power of hell or scheme of man can pluck us from his hand. (Rom. 8:29-30; Rom. 9-11; Eph. 1; John 6)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Limited (Particular) Atonement?",
    "answer": "A. Limited (Particular) Atonement is the doctrine that Christ by his death paid the penalty for the elect, and not for those who would be condemned to hell. (John 6:37, 44-46, 65; Rom. 11; Eph. 1)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Irresistible Grace?",
    "answer": "A. Irresistible Grace is the doctrine that those to whom God calls in his saving grace cannot resist and his call if fully efficacious. (John 6:65; Rom. 11; Eph. 2:8-9)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Perseverance of the Saints?",
    "answer": "A. Perseverance of the Saints is the doctrine that those who are called will remain regenerate in this life, and cannot completely fall away. (James; Eph. 2:10)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the difference between total depravity, partial depravity, and absolute depravity?",
    "answer": "A. Total depravity means all aspects of humanity are affected by the fall, yet man is not as bad as he can be due to God's common grace. Partial depravity means some aspects are affected, while part good. Absolute depravity means man is completely and utterly depraved in all aspects."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the relationship between God's sovereignty and man's responsibility?",
    "answer": "A. God is an all-knowing and fully sovereign God, yet humanity is responsible for turning from sin and towards God, confessing Jesus Christ as Lord, and following Him, with two extreme positions (hyper-Calvinist and Arminian) erring by overemphasizing one or the other."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the error of hyper-Calvinism?",
    "answer": "A. Hyper-Calvinism overemphasizes God's sovereignty, erring on the side of not evangelizing and calling people to repent and follow Christ, because God will ultimately save those he has ordained to save, and fails to consider the means by which God has chosen to spread the seed of the gospel."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the error of Arminianism?",
    "answer": "A. Arminianism struggles to account for God's sovereignty and the sinful estate of humanity, emphasizing human responsibility and capacity in responding to the gospel call, and fails to recognize that those who repent and are delivered from sin do not merit it of their own efforts but are indebted solely to the grace of God."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the extent of God's sovereignty?",
    "answer": "A. God has ordained whatsoever comes to pass, but does not destroy the will of the creature, nor has he decreed based on something foreseen in the future."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Does God grieve when Christ is rejected?",
    "answer": "A. In one sense, God is grieved by Israel's rejection of God, but God is impassible and not subject to pain or suffering, and His grief is not the same as human grief."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is covenant theology and what is a covenant?",
    "answer": "A. Covenant theology is the way in which God relates to humankind and stresses the unity of God’s plan of redemption throughout the entirety of Scripture. Though there are particular covenants, each of them serves God’s greater, overarching covenant of redemption throughout all of Scripture.<br><br>Covenant – A binding contract between two parties which has stipulations and actions required of each party. “A bond in blood sovereignly administered.”"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. How is covenant theology expressed in the Westminster Confession of Faith?",
    "answer": "A. The WCF does not touch on the Covenant of Redemption. In WCF 7, the Divine's teach the necessity for the covenant relationship because mankind needs the condescension of God to even glorify him."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is union with Christ and what is its relationship with the ordo salutis?",
    "answer": "A. Union with Christ is the central doctrine of salvation in which the Holy Spirit unites us to Christ, so as God looks at us, He sees the work and righteousness of Jesus, and from which the redemptive benefits of Christ, or ordo salutis, 'spring.'"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the definition and biblical support for the ordo salutis as a whole and in each of its parts?",
    "answer": "A. Whole: Rom. 8:28-29 (union with Christ: Rom. 6, 8:9)<br>Election: Eph. 1, 2<br>Calling: Rom. 1:6<br>Regeneration: Jn. 3<br>Faith/Repentance (Conversion): Acts 2, Acts 11; Rom. 1:17<br>Justification: Rom. 3<br>Adoption: Rom. 8<br>Sanctification: Rom. 6:19, 1 Cor. 6<br>Glorification: Rom 8"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Define the outward and inward calls of the gospel.",
    "answer": "A. The outward call of the gospel is any sharing of the gospel and proclamation of the good news and is like the seed broadcast, not determined by the hearer’s response.<br>The inward call of the gospel is the working of the Holy Spirit in the individual’s heart, regenerating them and giving the gift of faith and repentance."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is sin?",
    "answer": "A. Sin is any want of conformity unto, or transgression of, the law of God. (WSC 14)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is repentance?",
    "answer": "A. Repentance unto life is a saving grace, whereby a sinner, out of a true sense of his sin, and apprehension of the mercy of God in Christ, does, with grief and hatred of his sin, turn from it unto God, with full purpose of, and endeavor after, new obedience. (WSC 87)<br><br>No sinner may expect pardon apart from repentance (Luke 13:3)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Define faith and repentance. What is their relationship?",
    "answer": "A. Faith is trusting in God’s promises of salvation, believing though not seeing. Repentance is acknowledging sin and turning from it unto Christ. It is not mere remorse. Faith and repentance are fruits of the Spirit’s regeneration, and one is not present without the other."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is justification?",
    "answer": "A. Justification is an act of God's free grace in which he pardons our sins, accepts us as righteous in his sight, for the righteousness of Christ imputed to us and received by faith (WSC 33; Rom. 3:24; 2 Cor. 5:21; Phil. 3:9)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the relation of good works to faith?",
    "answer": "A. Good works are the fruit and evidence of faith (James 2:18, 22). James and Romans approach justification from different perspectives, with good works being the justification, or vindication, of faith."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the doctrine of sanctification?",
    "answer": "A. The work of God's grace whereby the whole person is renewed in the image of God and are enabled more and more to die unto sin and live unto righteousness (WSC 35; Ezek. 36:25-27; Rom. 6:6)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the relationship between justification and baptism?",
    "answer": "A. Justification is an act on God's part, while baptism is a sacrament and a sign and seal of the covenant of grace, and does not effectually save nor cause one to be justified."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Why is justification called an 'act' and sanctification a 'work'?",
    "answer": "A. Justification is an 'act' in that there is a moment in time in which an individual is moved from being condemned to justified, while sanctification is an ongoing work of God's grace that continues throughout the life of the believer."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Can anyone become perfect or be completely sanctified in this life?",
    "answer": "A. No, the corruption of sin remains, and the Christian continues in war against the flesh, though with the help of the Spirit. (Phil. 3:12; 1 John 1:10)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the relation of good works to faith?",
    "answer": "A. Good works are the fruit and evidence of faith (James 2:18, 22). James and Romans approach justification from different perspectives, with good works being the justification, or vindication, of faith."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Are good works necessary for salvation or may they save us?",
    "answer": "A. We would never be able to perform even the duty required (Luke 17:10).<br><br>Good works will not merit pardon from sin and cannot satisfy the debt of our prior sin (Eph 2:8-9)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Can a person be sure he is saved? Defend with scripture proofs.",
    "answer": "A. Yes, because their hope and assurance are in the promises of God (Heb 6:11-19; 1 John 3:24). It is the Christian’s duty (2 Peter 1:10)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. How could a person know he is saved? On what could such assurance be based?",
    "answer": "A. Assurance is grounded in the infallible assurance of faith, founded upon the promises of salvation, and is enabled by the Spirit with an internal witness."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What should a person do who lacks assurance of salvation?",
    "answer": "A. Daily repent of their sins and turn to Jesus, who offers life, with full assurance God will forgive our sins (1 John 1:9). While we desire to make our calling and election sure, our assurance is ultimately tied to the promises of God, who does not change."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are the three Confessional grounds for the assurance of salvation?",
    "answer": "A. By faith grounded upon the truth of God’s promises, by the Spirit enabling them to discern in themselves those graces to which the promises of life are made, and bearing witness with their spirits that they are the children of God (WLC 80)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is damnation?",
    "answer": "A. Eternal condemnation to hell."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the mission of the church?",
    "answer": "A. The mission of the church is to go into the world and make disciples by declaring the gospel of Jesus Christ in the power of the Spirit and gathering these disciples into churches, that they might worship and obey Jesus Christ now and in eternity to the glory of God the Father."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. How does Christian liberty bear on the Christian’s obligation to the state?",
    "answer": "A. If the power is lawful, and exercised in a lawful manner, the Christian has the responsibility to obey or else be found resisting the ordinance of God (WCF 20.4)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the 'regulative principle?' Defend with scripture proofs.",
    "answer": "A. The acceptable way of worshipping God is instituted by himself and therefore limited to his own revealed will, and that he is not to be worshipped according to the imaginations and devices of men, or the suggestions of Satan (Exod. 20; Deut. 12; Lev. 10; Matt. 15; Col. 2)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the moral law and its three uses?",
    "answer": "A. The moral law (contrasted with the ceremonial law) is the use of the Ten Commandments as the law setting norms for the people.<br>The three uses of the moral law are (1) as a mirror to reflect our own sinfulness and need for salvation, (2) as a 'civil use' to restrain evil and be a law for all people, and (3) to guide the Christian in good works and what pleases God."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Are believers under obligation to the law today? Defend with scripture proofs.",
    "answer": "A. Under the New Covenant, believers are not required to keep the ceremonial law as Christ was the once-for-all sacrifice (Heb.), but the moral law remains."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the state of man after death?",
    "answer": "A. At death, body and soul are separated. The souls of believers are received into heaven where they behold the face of Christ and wait for the redemption of their bodies. The wicked, at death, are cast into hell to endure torments until the resurrection and the judgment."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What are the major Millennial views?",
    "answer": "A. Amillennial – The millennium describes the present reign of the souls of deceased believers with Christ in heaven. The present form of God’s kingdom will be followed by Christ’s return, the general resurrection, the final judgment, and Christ’s continuing reign over the perfect kingdom on the new earth in the eternal state.<br>Pre-Millennial – The present form of God’s kingdom is moving toward a grand climax when Christ will return, the first resurrection will occur, and his kingdom will find expression in a literal, visible reign of peace and righteousness on the earth in space-time history. After the final resurrection, the last judgment, and the renewal of the heavens and the earth, this future, temporal kingdom will merge into the eternal kingdom, and the Lord will reign forever on the new earth.<br>  - Historical Premillennialism – view of many church fathers<br>  - Dispensational Premillennialism (Pre-tribulation) – Secret/invisible rapture of the church with a 7-year tribulation then restored theocracy of Israel with a true thousand-year reign<br>Post-Millennial – The world will eventually be Christianized, resulting in a long period of peace and prosperity called the millennium. This future period will close with Christ’s second coming, the resurrection of the dead, the final judgment, and the eternal state."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the difference between dispensational premillennialism and covenantal premillennialism?",
    "answer": "A. The main difference between dispensational and covenantal premillennialism is the sharp distinction between Jew and Gentile that the former maintains. Covenantal premillennialism asserts that there is one people of God comprised of both Jews and Gentiles that will find its fulfillment in the millennium. Dispensational premillennialism, on the other hand, claims that the millennium will concern primarily the establishment of a Jewish kingdom."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. Are there gifts mentioned in Scripture not given today and what were their purpose?",
    "answer": "A. Yes! Certain gifts mentioned in scripture (prophecy [as revelation], tongues, miracles, healing) seem to be strictly associated with the establishment of apostolic authority and the church. These gifts were given to reveal God’s gospel message and to confirm the messenger and his message."
  }
]
